Guide to the Montana Office of the State Controller records 1958-1971
Montana Historical Society
Montana Office of the State Controller records
1958-1971
RS 138 (28:5-3)
Montana. Office of the State Controller
.7 linear feet of shelf space
The Montana State Controller served as the state's accountant and ex-officio purchasing agent. Records (1958-1971) consist of correspondence with state agencies; interoffice correspondence; subject files concerning the Statewide Budgeting and Accounting System (SBAS), the Centennial Train, Governor's office remodeling, building codes, state institutions, etc.
In 1951 the Montana Legislative Assembly created the Office of State Controller to assume the duties of the state accountant. The controller was appointed by the governor for an eight year term and was directed to establish a system of financial control, install a uniform accounting and reporting system, examine appropriation requests, and submit a revised and final budget to the legislature. The controller was also the ex-officio state purchasing agent.
The 1963 legislature created a Department of Administration to provide "a more coordinated, responsible, efficient and economical organization by centralizing and consolidating the general administrative and fiscal functions of state government into one department." The state controller was made the chief executive of the department, with divisions for accounting, purchasing, architecture and engineering, and general services. The controller became responsible for centralized mailing and telephone systems for state government, allocation of office space, custodial care of the Capitol and other state property, records management for state records, preparation of building programs, appointments of architects, supervision of construction and renovation of state buildings, disposal of state property (including the Montana Centennial Train), purchasing of major equipment for state agencies, and distribution of surplus commodities.
The controller also oversaw several advisory bodies including a council to create construction standards for state buildings (this later became the Building Code Council), a fiscal coordinating committee, a personnel study committee, the State Board of Review which studied pro rata charges, and a committee on data processing equipment which worked to coordinate the selection of computer systems and equipment in state government. As a result of this latter committee, a Data Processing Division was created within the Department of Administration. A Management Systems Unit was also created and worked to produce the Statewide Budget and Accounting System (SBAS) that went into operation in 1972.
As a result of the Executive Reorganization Act passed in 1971, the Department of Administration was reconstituted and the title state controller was changed to director.
Those serving as state controller included W.F. Koch, Walter Anderson, Ralph Kenyon, Doyle B. Saxby, H.F. (Mike) Weggenbaum, and Jack Crosser.
This collection contains records of the Office of the State Controller including general correspondence (1958-1971) with state agencies, the governor, and members of the Legislative Assembly; interoffice correspondence (1965-1971) between the controller and other members of the Department of Administration staff; subject files (1961-1971) relating to state agencies, advisory bodies, and specific projects (e.g., SBAS, surplus commodities); miscellany (1961-1969, undated); and clippings (1968-1969).
The collection is arranged by series.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information is available upon request.
Printed material transferred to Library.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Capitols--Montana; Information storage and retrieval systems--Montana; Surplus commodities--Montana
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
- General Correspondence
  - "To All State Agencies", 1961-1971 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - "Attorney General", 1962-1971 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - "Budget Director", 1965-1971 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Department of Fish and Game, 1966-1971 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - "Governor's Office" (includes controller's annual statistical report for 1959-1960 and summary of activities for 1960-1968), 1958-1971 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - "Legislative Assembly" (includes Legislative Audit Committee and legislative auditor), 1963-1971 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - State Board of Examiners, 1961-1971 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - University System, 1965-1971, undated (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1961-1971, undated (Box-folder 1 / 9)
- Interoffice Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, 1965-1971 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
- Printed Materials
  - List of printed materials transferred to the Library (Box-folder 1 / 11)
- Subject Files
  - "Accounting System" (re Statewide Budgeting and Accounting System), 1968-1971 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - "Automatic Data Processing" (includes a speech by Doyle B. Saxby), 1965-1971 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - "Blanket Bond" (re Public Employees Faithful Performance Blanket Bond), 1965-1966 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
  - "Capitol Expansion" (includes governor's office remodeling), 1965-1968 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - "Centennial Train" (re disposal of Montana Centennial Train), 1963-1971 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - Controller's Advisory Committee on Data Processing Equipment, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - Controller's Advisory Council on Building Code; Building Code Council, 1963-1971 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - "Department of Administration Recodification" (includes descriptions of divisions done for Commission on Executive Reorganization; organization chart), 1969-1971, undated (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - Department of Institutions (re Swan River Youth Forest Camp, Montana Veterans' Home, etc.), 1961-1971 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - "Fiscal Coordinating Committee", 1968-1970 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
  - Governor's Conference on Data Processing; Statewide Data Processing Conference (includes a speech by Doyle B. Saxby), 1970 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
  - "Personnel Study" (includes Advisory Committee for the Personnel Study), 1967-1968 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - "Senate Desks" (re sale of desks to counties, etc.), 1967-1969 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
  - State Board of Review (re pro rata charges, etc.), 1971 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
  - "Surplus Commodities", 1961-1969 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
  - "Path of claims and resulting warrant" chart; "comparisons of work handled" by Purchasing and State Accounting Divisions statistics; Department of Administration information questionnaire; chart illustrating purchasing procedure for Purchasing Division; mailing list for controller's biennial report, 1965-1967, undated (Box-folder 2 / 15)
  - Building program time schedule; "number of state employees" list; list of "office space leased by the State of Montana"; list of major state government programs by function; list of architectural appointments, 1961, 1969, undated (Box-folder 2 / 16)
  - White Sulphur Springs Airport (re invitation to bid), 1966 (Box-folder 2 / 17)
- Clippings
  - Miscellaneous, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 2 / 18)